Guide to the Transport Workers Union of America, Local 100: Joseph Gayol Files WAG.085
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Transport Workers Union of America, Local 100: Joseph Gayol Files
1962-1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gayol, Joseph
Newman, Dave
WAG.085
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
The collection contains materials collected by Joseph Gayol, an activist in rank and file movements in the Transport Workers Union of America, Local 100. The collection is comprised largely of campaign flyers and circulars distributed to Local 100 members by dissident rank and file candidates. Also included are grievance forms, correspondence, contracts and agreements.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dave Newman, Communication Workers Union rank and file worker, 1983. The accession number associated with this gift is 1983.004.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The collection contains materials collected by Joseph Gayol, an activist in rank-and-file movements in Transport Workers Union of America, Local 100.
Joseph Gayol, a subway car maintenance worker, became involved in the rank-and-file movement of Local 100 in 1978. In anticipation of the 1979 Local elections, Gayol joined with nine other rank-and-file workers at the 207th Street Shop. They collected grievances as evidence that the Transit Authority (TA) and TWU leaders were derelict in not providing adequate attention to safety issues and to protection of transit workers. With the intent of taking the TA and TWU to court, they organized a Health and Safety Committee associated with the George McDonald slate.
Though the Health and Safety Committee was very popular, they felt their efforts were stymied as McDonald continually postponed or incorrectly filed their proposals for action. In an endeavor to move forward they switched their allegiance to the Unity slate but eventually became disillusioned with that group as well.
Greatly factionalized, each of the contending slates lost its momentum and failed to build a united coalition of dissidents. A combination of racial, political and divisional conflicts prevented the rank-and-file groups from backing a single slate. As a result, incumbent John Lawe maintained his office as president of Local 100, winning 9,781 votes compared to the 13,076 split among the three rank-an-file slates.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is comprised largely of campaign flyers and circulars distributed to Local 100 members by various candidates. Grievance forms, correspondence, contracts and agreements are also present in the collection.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, General Files, 1962-1980.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Transport Workers Union of America: Records of Locals (Wagner #234)
Correspondence.; Contracts; Fliers (printed matter); Forms (documents); Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State); New York (N.Y.).; Transport workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100; Newman, Dave
- Series I: General Files, 1962-1980.
  - Agreement: TWU-- New York City Transit Authority and Manhattan and Bronx Surface Transit Operating Authority (MABSTOA), 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Benefits, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Coalition of Concerned Transit Workers: Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coalition of Concerned Transit Workers: Flyers, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Coalition of Concerned Transit Workers: Forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Coalition of Concerned Transit Workers: Newsletters, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coalition of Concerned Transit Workers: Petition for Removal of Local 100 Officers, May 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Committee for a Democratic Union: Flyers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Contracts, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Elections, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Flyers, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Grievance Forms, undated, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Grievances, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Health and Safety Committee: Flyers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Humphrey, Walter Slate: Flyers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 832: Flier, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jones, Herbert Slate :Flyers, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lawe, John: Correspondence and Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lawe, John Slate :Flyers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - McDonald, George J.: Legal Retainer and Check Copies, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - McDonald, George J. Slate: Flyers, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - McDonald, George J. Slate: Pocket Protector, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Meeting Notice Flyers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH): Publications, 1972, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Organizational Chart (TWU), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Press Releases, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Robinson, Felix, et al., v. New York City Transit Authority, et al. - Preliminary Injunction and Restraining Order, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Santo Defense Committee Membership Card (J. Lynch), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sick Leave Forms, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Station Team - Flyers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Transit Workers Coalition (207th Street Transit Workers Coalition) - Flyers, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Transit Workers Coalition (207th Street Transit Workers Coalition) - Member List, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Transit Workers Coalition (207th Street Transit Workers Coalition) - The Soap Box(Newsletter), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - The Unity Slate - Flyers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Unity Slate - General (Notes, Agendas, Contracts), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Unity Slate - Publications, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)